Henry J. Hart Collection
Henry J. Hart Collection
1869-1928
Hart, Henry J.
4.5 linear feet
Material relating to real estate and investments in central New York
5483850
Biographical History
Henry J. Hart (dates unknown) was a real estate agent and estate executor in Syracuse, New York in the early 20th century. He is listed in Jackson's Real Estate Directory, 1912-1913 edition, as having offices at 68 Wieting Block. He served as the city's Commissioner of Deeds from 1911-1913 (Proceedings of the Common Council of the City of Syracuse, FY 1911, p. 13), and according to The Real Estate Magazine, Volume 4 (Nov 1914), p. 78 was a delegate to the state's first convention of real estate businessmen. His name also appears in the U.S. Patent Registry as part owner of a patent for an automatic car brake (US Pat. No. 661,435, filed Feb 20, 1900).His wife, Adeline Hart, worked along side Hart in his real estate business.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Henry J. Hart Collection is separated into Hart's papers and those of others.
The first series consists of Henry J. Hart's business records, the clients for whom he was executor, and his personal financial accounts and correspondence. In the business records subseries, the contracts folders consist of contracts conducted between a second part and either Hart himself or his wife Adeline.
The second series consist of contracts between other, that is individuals not Hart or Adeline. Also within this series are a few blueprints and urban development plans created by unknown companies.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by name or type of material and within each folder chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Business and Industry; Hart, Henry J.; Real estate business -- New York (State); Property.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- History.; Contracts.; Property records.; Account books.; Correspondences.; Tax returns.; Checks (bank checks); Blueprints (reprographic copies); Real estate agent.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advance notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2015.
Inventory
- Henry J. Hart
  - Business records
    - Appraisals, 1904-1921; 2 folders (Oversize 1)
    - Appraisals, 1919-1923 (Box 1)
    - Contracts, 1907; 1910-1923; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Financial material, 1905-1925; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Residence property book, 1917-1922; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook, circa 1915-1925; newspaper clippings of Hart's advertisments and handwritten notes on numerous types of potential properties (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1915-1925; clippings, financial material, and ink stamp; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Clients
    - Hampton, Jennie M., 1911; 1916-1925; correspondence, contracts, financial material, miscellaneous; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Overacker, Susan, 1926-1928; correspondence, court documents, financial material; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Wilcox, Emmaline, 1913-1923; estate account (Box 2)
  - Personal
    - Correspondence, 1915; 1926 (Box 2)
    - Date book, circa 1910-1920 (Box 2)
    - Financial material
      - Account ledgers, 1898; 1915-1928; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Account ledger, circa 1915-1925 (Oversize 2)
      - Income tax, 1919-1923 (Box 3)
      - Income tax, 1918-1924 (Oversize 3)
- Others
  - Allen, Orpha C., 1918-1922 (Box 3)
  - Cage, Elizabeth, 1917-1919 (Box 3)
  - Fellows, Nellie L., 1918-1919 (Box 3)
  - Fellows, William G., 1906; 1908,; 1915-1918,; 1923-1925 (Box 3)
  - Blueprints of homes in Syracuse, undated (Box 3)
  - Blueprints of homes and urban development in Syracuse, undated (Oversize 3)
  - Contracts, miscellaneous, 1874; 1892,; 1902,; 1908,; 1911-1916; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Contracts, miscellaneous, 1920-1928; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1869; 1905,; 1921-1923; court documents and abstract of titles (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1910; 1913,; 1916-1918,; 1920-1922,; 1927-1928; other individual receipts, blank forms, and handwritten notes (Box 4)